Guide to the James Dolsen Political Left Pamphlets Collection, 1918-1996 AIS.1999.11
ULS Archives & Special Collections
James Dolsen Political Left Pamphlets Collection
1918-1996
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Dolsen, James H.
AIS.1999.11
6.25 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
James Dolsen was a founding member of the Communist Party USA and was persecuted during the 1930s and 1950s for his involvement in Communist activities. This collection contains pamphlets, newsletters, and newspapers from various organizations concerning unemployment, socialism and deindustrialization.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Mark Dolsen in 1999.
Biography
James Dolsen was a founding member of the Communist Party USA. He served as Secretary-Treasurer of the Workers Alliance of Allegheny County and District Secretary of the International Labor Defense, in addition to being affiliated with several Communist organizations in the Pittsburgh, Pa., area. Dolsen was also a correspondent for the Daily Worker, the newspaper of the Communist Party USA. He was questioned by the Dies Committee and the House Un-American Activities Committee regarding his work as a Communist leader. In the early 1950s, Dolsen was convicted of sedition along with Steve Nelson and served several years in a workhouse before a new trial was demanded by the United States Supreme Court due to the unreliable testimony of FBI informant Joseph Mazzei. Dolsen lived to be 103 years old and was an active member in the Communist party until his death in 1988.
Previous Citation
James Dolsen Political Left Pamphlets Collection, 1918-1996, AIS.1999.11, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Related Material
Steve Nelson Oral History Project Records, AIS.1978.24, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Hymen Schlesinger Papers, 1927-1990, AIS.1977.33, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
A. E. Forbes Communist Collection, 1921-1972, AIS.2000.07, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Lawrence F. Evans Collection, 1978-1988, AIS.1988.17, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
The American Left Emphemera Collection
Scope and Content Notes
This collection contains pamphlets, newsletters, and newspapers from various organizations concerning unemployment, socialism and deindustrialization. Included are various socialist newspapers, including The Militant and Labor Action, and other left publications from the 1950s. Information on deindustrialization in Pittsburgh during the 1980s can be found in subject files such as those regarding the Tri-State Conference on Steel. There are also several files regarding labor unions in the Pittsburgh area.
Pamphlets; Social action; Communists -- United States; Labor; Labor unions and communism -- United States; Communism -- United States; Socialism -- United States; Socialists -- United States; Labor unions and socialism -- United States; Tri-State Conference on Steel; Dolsen, James H.
- The Class Struggle, 1918 (Box 1, Volume 1-2)
- Partisan Review, August-September 1938 (Box 1, Volume 3)
- The Communist International (Box 1, Volume 4)
- Marxist Perspectives, September 1980 (Box 1, Volume 5)
- Mimeographed Letters, 1945-1948 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Civil Rights Defense Committee, Pittsburgh Chapter, 1942-1944 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Daniel de Leon Pamphlets (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Union Agreements, 1974-1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Socialist Publications (Box 1, Folder 5)
- United Engineering and Foundry Company (Box 1, Folder 6)
- United Steelworkers of America, 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- The Hilltop, January 1949 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- CCU Newsletter by the Committee of Concerned Unionists, 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Just Harvest, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Tri-State Conference on Steel, 1985-1989 (Box 1, Folder 11-15)
- Western Pennsylvania Alliance to Block Bork, Steel Valley Authority and DMX (Box 1, Folder 16)
- McKeesport Coalition for the Homeless (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Miscellaneous Reference (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Social Security "Notch", 1987 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Pennsylvania Alliance for Jobs and Energy, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Activities (Box 1, Folder 21)
- The Pennsylvania Activist, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Economy (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Religion, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- LTV Plant Closures (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Workers Compensation, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Senior Citizens Health Care (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Miscellaneous Newsletters, 1985, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
- Mon Valley Unemployed Committee, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Trotsky Articles (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Newsletters regarding Women's Issues, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- The Scab (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Women of Steel, November 1979 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Federation For Industrial Retention & Renewal, 1990-1994 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- The Newsletter of Pittsburgh Action Against Rape, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Allegheny Socialist by the Institute for Democratic Socialism, 1987-1991 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- N.U.W.O. Bulletin by the National United Workers Organization (Box 2, Folder 8)
- 1397 Rank & File by USWA Local 1397, 1977-1978, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- City Times, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- The Voice by USWA Local 1256, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Convoy Dispatch by Teamsters for a Democratic Union, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- From the Horse's Mouth by Western Pennsylvania Teamsters for a Democratic Union, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Local 1010 Steelworker, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- The Steelworker, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Tri-State Conference on Steel Newsletter, 1981, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Against the Current, 1991-1993 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Bulletin in Defense of Marxism, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 18-20)
- Labor Notes, 1979-1981, 1988-1996 (Box 2, Folder 21-22)
- New American Movement Pittsburgh Chapter Newsletter, 1977-1981 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Resistance, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- United Effort by United Engineering and Foundry Company, 1947-1957 (Box 2, Folder 25-27)
- Dravo Review, 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Miscellaneous Union Newspapers, 1957, 1981, 1990, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Solidarity by the United Autoworkers, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Miscellaneous Labor Newspapers (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Mill Hunk Herald, 1979-1987 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Social Justice by the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- United Mine Workers Journal, 1956, 1985-1987, 1991-1993 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Socialist Action, 1991-1993 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- Why? An Anarchist Bulletin, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Internal Bulletin of the Socialist Workers Party, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Fourth International, 1942-1954 (Box 3, Folder 10-11)
- Anvil and Student Partisan, 1950-1953 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- IUE News, 1976-1981 (Box 3, Folder 13-15)
- Changes Socialist Monthly, 1979 (Box 4, Volume 1-2)
- Tricolor, May 1944 (Box 4, Volume 3)
- Tri-State Council on Manufacturing (Box 4, Folder 1)
- New American Movement (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Labor Solidarity, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Clippings (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Labor Party Advocates (Box 4, Folder 5)
- New Directions by the United Autoworkers, 1990 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- US-China People's Friendship Association, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- UFCW Local 23, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Steelworkers Voice, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- Alliance for Progressive Action, 1992-1993 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- Newsletter from Christians Associated for Relationships with Eastern Europe's Christian-Marxist Encounter Task Group (Box 4, Folder 11)
- Fox Chapel Federation of Teachers, Local 2028 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Somerville Mills Boycott (Box 4, Folder 13)
- Miscellaneous Newsletters (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Miscellaneous Newspapers, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 15)
- Miscellaneous Newsletters and Newspapers (Box 4, Folder 16)
- United Steelworkers of America (Box 4, Folder 17)
- Tri-State Conference on the Impact of Steel (Box 4, Folder 18)
- The Reporter, 1949, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- The Permanent Revolution in Science by R.L. Schanak (Box 4, Folder 20)
- Labor and Nation, 1946, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- National Committee for Independent Political Action, 1989-1990 (Box 4, Folder 22)
- J.P. Stevens Company Information (Box 4, Folder 23)
- Dollars & Sense, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 24)
- Reference, New (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Teamsters for a Democratic Union (Box 4, Folder 26)
- Songs by Michael Stout, 1988-1992 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Hunger Action Coalition (Box 4, Folder 28)
- Rathbum for Mayor (Box 4, Folder 29)
- James Dolson v. United Engineering and Foundry Company, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- Ed Sadlowski for USWA President (Box 4, Folder 31)
- World's Greatest Fairshake Festival III, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 32)
- Miscellaneous Contract Agreements (Box 4, Folder 33)
- Fliers (Box 4, Folder 34)
- IUE Research (Box 4, Folder 35)
- Articles on Labor at Westinghouse (Box 4, Folder 36)
- Miscellaneous Research (Box 4, Folder 37)
- Personal Calendar, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 38)
- The Militant, 1953-1954 (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
- The Militant, 1980-1981 (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
- Labor Action, August 1953-March 1954 (Box 5, Folder 6-7)
- Steel Labor, 1969, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Steel Labor/Steelabor, 1977-1979 (Box 5, Folder 9-11)
- Daily World/People's Daily World, 1978, 1981, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Workers Vanguard, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 13-14)